Girl,
what's your sole purpose in this army? To
do whatever you tell, my drill sergeant? Goddamn
it, Gump. You're a goddamn genius. That's the
most outstanding answer I've ever heard. You must
have a goddamn IQ of a 160.
Who in the hell is that? Down there
is Forrest Gump, coach.
Now maybe it's just me, but college was
very confusing times.
You ever been on a real shrimp boat?
No.
But I've been on a real big boat.
I'm talking about a shrimp catching, but
I've been working on shrimp boats all my
life. I started out on my uncle's boat.
That's my mama's brother when I was about
maybe 9. I was just looking in the
buying a boat of my own and got
drafted.
My given name is Benjamin Beaufort Blue. People
call me Bubba.
Just like one of them old redneck boys.
Can you believe that? My name's Forrest Gump.
People call me Forrest Gump.
So Bubba was from Bayou La Batre, Alabama
and his mama cooked shrimp.
And her mama before her cooked shrimp.
And her mama before her mama cooked shrimp
too. Bubba's family knew everything there was to
know about the shrimping business. I know everything
there is to know about the shrimping business.
Matter of fact, I'm going into the shrimping
business for myself after I get out the
army.
Okay. Girl,
what's your sole purpose in this army? To
do whatever you tell my drill sergeant? Goddamn
it, Gump. You're a goddamn genius. That's the
most outstanding answer I've ever heard. You must
have a goddamn IQ of a 160. You
are goddamn gifted, Private Gump.
Listen up people.
Now for some reason I fit in the
army like one of them round pegs. It's
not really hard. You just make your bed
real neat and remember to stand up straight,
and always answer every question with, yes, drill
sergeant. Isn't that clear? Yes, drill sergeant.
What you do is you just drag your
nets along the buck. On a good day,
you can catch over a £100 of shrimp.
Everything goes alright. 2 men shrimp in 10
hours. Less with 2 shimps on gas.
Tundra, sergeant? Yes. Go on.
Why did you put that weapon together so
quickly, god? You tell me to do your
target? Jesus H Christ. This is a new
company record. If it wouldn't be a waste
of such a damn fine enlisted men, I'd
recommend you for OCS Private Gump. You are
gonna be a general someday Gump. Now, there's
a simple your weapon to continue.
Anyway, like I was saying, shrimp is the
fruit of the sea. You can barbecue it,
boil it, broil it, bake it, saute it.
There's shrimp kebabs, shrimp creole, shrimp gumbo,
pan fried, deep fried, stir
fried. There's pineapple shrimp,
lemon shrimp, coconut shrimp, pepper shrimp, shrimp soup,
shrimp stew, shrimp salad,
shrimp and potatoes,
shrimp burger, shrimp sandwich.
That's that's about it.
And every time I went back looking for
Bubba, somebody else was saying, help me, Forrest.
Help me.
I
started to get scared that I might never
find Buckle. Back there, over. Strong-arm. I know
my position is danger close. We got Charlie
all over this area. I gotta have those
fast movers in here now, over. Jack, strong-arm.
We want Lieutenant dad, call this dad. I
know he's dead. My old goddamn platoon is
wiped out. What
are you doing? What are you doing?
You'll leave me here. Get away. Just leave
me here. Get out. Strong-arm. I'll tell him.
God, I said leave me here. Goddamn it.
Likely, mister. Likely, mister. Strong-arm. Be advised your
passengers are inbound at this time. Over. Then
it felt like something just jumped up and
bit
think son of a bitch?
Yes.
I can't leave the platoon. I told you
to leave me there, Gump. Forget about me.
Get yourself out. Did you hear what I
said?
Goddamn it. Put me down.
Get your ass out of here.
Get your ass out of here. I didn't
ask you to pull me out of there.
Goddamn you. Where the hell do you think
you're going? Get Bob. I got an airstrike
inbound right now. They're gonna nape the whole
area.
Don't you stay here. Goddamn it. That's an
order. I gotta find Bob.
Forest.
Okay, Forest.
I'm okay.
Uh-oh. But no. No. I'm gonna be alright.
If I'd have known this was gonna be
the last time me and Bubba was gonna
talk, I'd have thought of something better to
say. Hey, Bubba.
Hey, Forrest.
Forrest,
why didn't this happen?
You got shot.
Then Bubba said something I won't ever forget.
I wanna go home.
Bubba was my best good friend,
and even I know that ain't something you
can find just around the corner.
Bubba was gonna be a shrimp and buck
captain, but
instead, he died right there by that rhythm
of Vietnam.
Are you telling me you're the owner of
the Bubba Gump Shrimp Corporation? Yes, sir. We
got more money than the David Crockett.
Boy, I heard some bumpers in my time,
but that tops them all.
We were sitting next to a millionaire.
Well,
I thought it was a very lovely story,
and you tell it so well with such
enthusiasm.
Would you like to see what Loutek Dan
looks like? Well, yes. I would.
That's him right there.