This was a massive attack across the country
this morning. More than 200 missiles and drones,
not targeting the military though, but ordinary civilians.
Families who are now gonna struggle with shortages
of power and heating as temperatures here start
to plummet.
This morning, Russia launching 1 of its largest
attacks against Ukraine in months, missiles targeting power
plants and energy infrastructure
across the country,
sending people fleeing to metro stations and shelters.
The grid in Kiev and at least 1
other region forced to shut down, and Poland's
military scrambling its air force in response to
the attack.
The strikes signaling Russia's threat to leave millions
without power as freezing temperatures begin to grip
Ukraine.
Amid escalating attacks and Russian advances on the
battlefield,
intense conversations about possible negotiations to end this
war once president-elect Donald Trump takes office.
Ukrainian President Zelensky says he believes the end
of the war will be closer after Trump's
inauguration,
saying the war will end, but there's no
exact date. Certainly, with the policy of this
team that's about to lead the White House,
the war will end faster.
But Zelensky also warning that Ukraine must be
kept in a strong position and that the
US can't expect them to just Sit and
listen.