This is one of the world's most dangerous
roads,
and it leads to a place on Earth
like no other, a place where trees cannot
grow,
where ice shapes the land in bizarre and
otherworldly ways,
and only life supremely adapted to the cold
can survive.
The Dalton Highway of Alaska pushes far beyond
the Arctic Circle, a lifeline carved through harsh
and unforgiving terrain, existing and only existing because
of this, one of the single greatest engineering
feats of all time.
Our destination is the very end of the
road, where the edge of North America meets
the Arctic Ocean. The question is, can we
make it in one piece?
In 5 years living on the road, we
have never put our bus through a test
like this.
Come make the journey with us. Experience part
of the world few has seen and join
us in finding out what it's like to
drive Alaska's most feared road. Into the Arctic
we go, welcome aboard.
This is not your average road trip. The
Dalton Highway stretches 414 miles across the most
remote expanse of the Alaskan Arctic. We will
pass through the boreal forest, cross the Arctic
Circle, climb a steep and dangerous pass over
Alaska's northernmost mountain range, then cross the vast
Arctic tundra to finally reach the Arctic Ocean.
There are only 3 small settlements along the
route, 2 places to fuel up, and no
services. When venturing to a remote place like
this, anything could go wrong, so you must
prepare for the worst, but hope for the
best.
Before we get on the Dalton, we make
an important stop 9 miles north of Fairbanks,
Alaska. The Dalton Highway cannot be explored nor
appreciated without understanding its role and connection to
the Trans Alaska Pipeline.
It's hard to express just how groundbreaking the
construction and engineering of this pipeline was. This
single silver thread stretches 800 miles from the
edge of the Arctic Ocean to the ice
free port of Valdez, Alaska in the South.
Traverses 3 mountain ranges, 500 rivers and streams,
and 4 major fault and earthquake zones.
Here at this site, we are allowed to
walk right up to the pipeline, not a
replica, but the actual pipeline itself. As we
speak, 1,000 of dollars of crude oil are
flowing above our heads. We get to look
closely at its structure, in particular, these fin
like heat pipes that super chill the ground,
keeping the permafrost frozen and the pipeline stable.
We also see devices called PIGS that are
used to clean and inspect it from inside.
This older model was used in the early
pipeline. This model is used today.
In order to build the pipeline, a new
road had to be carved through one of
the most remote and harsh environments in the
world, a road which wasn't even open to
the public until 1994.
If you just found us now and you
are new to the channel, then welcome. We
are Cora and Jose, 2 artists with a
mission to take this beautiful beast from Alaska
to Argentina.
Bobby is our home and creative space on
wheels. If we can complete the Dalton with
no pop tires, no major breakdowns or toes,
and an intact windshield, we'll call that a
win.
We hit the road at mile 0 excited
for the journey ahead. Now the Dalton cannot
be done in a day. It is an
expedition that must be tackled in steps.
Our first major landmark will be the Yukon
River, 56 miles away, but we will stop
to sleep soon. Even though this is midnight
in early July, the dim light of nighttime
doesn't do this region justice. It's worth it
to take it slow because what we will
see between mile 0 and the Yukon deserves
to be explored by the bright light of
day.
The Dalton Highway spans 3 distinct regions, each
with its own plant and animal community adapted
to its environment.
Right now, we are in the taiga, also
known as the boreal forest.
The taiga is the largest forest ecosystem in
the world, forming a band that encircles the
entire northern hemisphere.
The first 50 miles of the Dalton cut
through the taiga, which is often called one
of the lungs of the planet. It covers
17% of Earth's land surface and stores twice
as much carbon per acre as tropical rain
forests. So far, the road is kind, but
we don't let our guard down. We're lucky
to be driving when the roads are dry.
The narrow packed lane and soft muddy shoulders
say it all. This road in the rain
would not be fun.
Before we know it, we arrive at a
force of the natural world, the Yukon River.
The mighty Yukon River is the longest river
in both Alaska and the Yukon Territory of
Canada.
It flows nearly 2,000 miles from its headwaters
in British Columbia through the Yukon, which is
named after the river, then through Alaska, where
it finally empties into the Bering Sea. To
give a sense of just how big and
powerful this river is, its average flow is
about a quarter of a 1000000 cubic feet
per second.
Despite its sheer length, there are only 4
vehicle bearing bridges that cross the Yukon, 3
are in Canada, and only one is in
Alaska.
The e l Patton Bridge was completed in
1975.
It is 2,295
feet long and 30 feet wide, a steel
girder bridge with a timber driving surface. It
transports both vehicles and the pipeline across the
Yukon. During construction of the bridge, a staging
area was established on the northern bank of
the Yukon, and a camp remains here to
this day. It's here to provide food and
lodging, and it's one of the 2 places
to fuel up on the entire route.
The cost of diesel today is a whopping
7.50 per gallon. If you can believe it,
this isn't the most expensive diesel we've ever
bought. 2 years ago, we paid over $9
a gallon driving up the Alaska highway.
Now, this is only one of 3 places
to eat on the entire Dalton Highway, so
we duck in to enjoy a hot meal.
We are a 135 miles from civilization, and
we can already feel the disconnect from the
rest of the world. Cell service ended a
long time ago, and even Internet isn't easy
to find.
The cafe at Yukon River Camp is humble
and cozy. We especially love seeing this wall
covered in handwritten signs from travelers across the
globe translating the original sign that kindly asks
visitors to stay out of the kitchen.
It's things like this, those little acts of
camaraderie that make the world a better place,
as do little acts of kindness. So we'd
like to take this moment to say thank
you to our new friends who surprised us
today and treated us to this delicious meal.
The next section of road is notorious for
its steep grades and often slick conditions.
Hills on this stretch have nicknames like beaverslide
and roller coaster.
If you're curious who named them, well, it's
important to understand that the Dalton is not
here for us. The road was built as
a supply route to the oil fields of
Prudhoe Bay. The bay is ice bound a
good portion of the year, so the main
way to transport all the tools, supplies, and
machinery for the massive operation up there is
by semi truck. That's why the road was
originally called the haul road, and the badass
truckers that drive it year round have names
for parts of the road. Names like Surprise
Rise, The Ice Cut, and O Shit Corner.
This is where we start to put our
bus to the test. The hills are deceiving.
They don't look steep until you're on them,
and the potholes make it really hard to
gain momentum. So it's a bit nerve wracking,
but our Bobby tackles hill after hill after
hill.
We make it to Finger Mountain, a place
of special significance, not realizing that tomorrow morning
we'll get a knock on the door from
a surprise visitor.
Now this encounter is one for the books.
Rewind a few weeks, and we are driving
through Alaska en route to Denali National Park.
We meet an ambitious young traveler from Germany
on a journey to ride his bicycle from
Vancouver Island to the Arctic Ocean. We joke
that we travel so slow in the bus
that he will probably beat us there, and
sure enough, he did.
Now here in a beautiful little traveler's twist
of fate, our paths cross again on the
Dalton. Us on our way up and Luis
on his way down.
Let's see here. Okay.
Please, look. You don't have to. Wait there.
Hold on. Hold
on.
Hold
on. Hold on. So you think in the
entire trip, this is, the toughest?
Yeah.
Well, I think the first gravel road, big
gravel road I've done. I mean, it's not
even gravel road. It's just mud.
It's a lot of time. Just mud,
especially with the rain. It's job.
I love it.
I love the adventure. Especially on this kind
of road, when it's a lonely road. Nowhere,
people take care of each other.
That's what I like. Mhmm. I'm excited to
go to South America too. Like,
my plan is to Canada and then maybe
work again and then down the states in
South America or South America.
I don't know. Alright. Ready for the road
again. Keep going.
Nice.
Alright. I got it.
Thank you, guys. Thank you so much.
That's a lot of things you're carrying in
this bike. Yeah. So,
here in front, I just just, I mean,
this is my tent. It's not a not
a good stuff, not the pro stuff, but
it's, you know, it's working. So
it's pretty
pretty basic. Like, what I got here.
It's just, it's a stove.
Wow. Just a stove, one pot.
And then some electronic devices here. Power banks,
drone.
And then my my my clothes are here.
Just, you know, my my suitcase.
And then I got my pillow,
my sleeping bag, mattress
in here. It's quite big. Everything it's not
like the small tiny stuff. And on the
other side, I carry some food too. So
I got all the bag full of food
and some food here and the stove and
the pot and that's it. And of course,
I got some small things to repair the
bike too. Some, yeah, tubes or whatever.
Carry this kind of things, rain pants.
Yeah. Nothing too crazy, but, yeah. But you
got everything you need in there? Everything I
need and, everything to survive. Easy.
My whole life.
Well, it's been awesome.
It was so nice to meet you guys.
Honestly, like, maybe see you on the road,
like, if if Canada, America, South America. Thank
you, Tom. I will be there. I will
be there. Yeah. We'll see you. And then
see you somewhere.
We have a feeling this isn't the last
time our story will share a page with
Luisa's. This is one of those beautiful and
also slightly tragic parts of life on the
road. When you meet a fellow nomad, you
get to connect with someone who really gets
you and you get them. There's an ease
and understanding that can be hard to find
elsewhere.
But then that same thing that brought you
together makes you say goodbye all too soon.
We spend a few days in the company
of Finger Mountain, an unmistakable landmark in this
wide open landscape.
Once upon a time, native peoples of the
interior knew it as a prime spot to
watch for game. Later, bush pilots used it
to aid in navigation, as the finger conveniently
points towards Fairbanks.
Finger Mountain, just like its neighbors near the
bus, is a granite tor, a block of
hard durable granite that resists erosion while everything
around it is more easily whittled away by
time.
This granite dates back a 110000000 years when
it first cooled from magma that crept into
cracks in the bedrock.
There will come a time in this drive
when we leave the trees behind, but we're
not there yet. The Finger Mountain area is
an upland region, rising just high enough above
the surrounding boreal forest that here, alpine tundra
prevails.
The tundra is dominated by hardy, ground hugging
plants that withstand hurricane force winds and temperatures
of 80 below 0,
and creatures that amazingly can withstand the same.
Every now and then, Willow Charmigan, Alaska's state
bird, pop in and out of the shrubbery.
These tough little fowl are currently in their
summer clothes, dappled brown to blend in with
the tundra. Come fall, their plumage will shift
to pure white to camouflage with the land
in its winter form.
One can only imagine this land in that
form, windswept and frozen, covered in pure white.
It must be quite a sight to behold.
Our goal today is to reach the mountains
and cross Adogan Pass. Snow falls year round
up there, so this hot sunny day just
might be our window to get over safely.
It's a 150 miles away, and there is
a whole lot to see between here and
there.
At mile 107, we pass Old Man Camp,
one of more than 31 working camps that
dotted the route during the pipeline's construction.
Now, most of them, like this one, are
little more than relics of the past.
The road shifts back and forth between gravel
and pavement.
And, honestly, it's hard to decide which is
preferable. The gravel has more potholes, but the
pavement is frost heavy.
Still, overall, the road is being kind. So
kind, in fact, that in no time, we
arrive at a big milestone of this journey.
We made it to the Arctic Circle. I
can't believe it has been almost 5 years
since we got on the road. Bobby bus
made it, and now here we are. Yeah.
And here's to hoping this old Florida bus
can get us now all the way up
to dead horse.
Okay. We're gonna leave a little baby Bobby
here at the Arctic Circle.
Right about there.
The Arctic Circle is an imaginary line that
circles the globe at approximately 66 degrees north
of the equator.
Here on this line, the sun never sets
on the summer solstice. The farther north you
go, the more days of 24 hour sunlight
you get until reaching the North Pole where
the sun doesn't set for a 180 days.
In the winter, the exact opposite is true.
We now push north of the Arctic Circle.
The amount of land up here is staggering.
3 national wildlife refuges and 1 national park
protect over 37,000,000
acres of land up here. Much of the
rest is state and Alaska native lands.
In the distance, we see a glimmer of
the challenge that lies ahead, crossing the Brooks
Range.
Just like the pipeline, we will have to
climb over that great boundary.
When the pipeline descends on this side of
the mountains, steep grades cause the oil to
speed up, and the pump station ahead plays
a critical role in reregulating flow.
In total, 12 pump stations are positioned along
the pipeline, each capable of moving 22,000
gallons of crude oil per minute.
4 of the pump stations are in use
today. And while most of them move oil
along, pump station 5 is charged with slowing
it down as thousands of gallons of hot
crude descend out of the Brooks Range.
Here, we also see a critical feature of
the pipeline's design, the Zig Zag Formation. This
allows for expansion or contraction of the pipeline
due to extreme temperature changes, as well as
play and movement during an earthquake.
We are still in the taiga, though approaching
its northern edge. In Alaska, the taiga is
dominated by spruce, but these tall skinny pipe
cleaners look a lot different from their Christmas
tree kin to the south.
Up here, spruce trees grow slender and far
apart to intercept the slanted sunlight that they
receive, and an acutely short summer forces them
to grow slow. Here, a tree that has
lived a 150 years may have a trunk
just 2 inches across.
We are now moving through the Jack White
Range, a mere prelude to the Brooks Range
just beyond.
The road continues to shift back and forth
between pavement and gravel. The biggest challenge is
not getting too comfortable on those smooth even
stretches that make you want to hit highway
speeds. It's tempting, but frost heaves and deep
potholes come out of nowhere, and this is
not a place to pop a tire or
break an axle.
In 1971, the coldest temperature ever recorded in
the United States was locked here along this
stretch of the road. The temperature reading came
in at a whopping negative 80 degrees Fahrenheit.
With daylight to spare, we arrive in Cold
Foot, Alaska, gateway to the Brooks Range.
Cold Foot is just about as sparse as
Yukon River Camp. It began as a gold
mining camp in 1900, and the story goes
that many miners got cold feet and turned
back after experiencing the harsh reality of winter
here.
The camp was abandoned with the discovery of
gold 10 miles north and it wasn't until
the construction of the pipeline that Cold Foot
was resurrected into construction camp. Today, it serves
as the last stop for food, fuel, and
water on the Dalton. There's a tire shop,
a trucker's cafe, humble lodging, and not much
else. After this lie 240 miles of pure
wilderness until dead horse.
Though there is an award winning gem just
across the road.
The Arctic Interagency Visitor Center is a partnership
between the National Park Service, the Bureau of
Land Management, and the US Fish and Wildlife
Service, and it is an amazing place.
This is where we dive deep into learning
about the unique and extreme environment of the
arctic. The margin for survival is narrow here,
and only the most supremely adapted species can
call this place home.
We are both excited and nervous for what
lies ahead. Excited because we are about to
leave the familiar behind and enter a strange
treeless land. But also nervous because this is
where we begin the climb into that Great
Wall of the North, the Brooks Range.
Today is the day we leave the taiga
behind and venture into that great barrier of
the North.
Sweeping like an arc across Alaska's Wild North,
these mountains separate 2 worlds, the Forrester Taiga
of the Interior and the vast treeless plains
of the Arctic.
At 700 miles long, they form America's longest
east west trending range and cover a 5th
of the state of Alaska, yet they are
so remote and so far north, only a
handful of communities call this place home.
Small lakes and ponds dotting the taiga are
actually thermokarsts,
sinkholes of the north. When ice in the
ground melts, craters
Sukukpak means marten deadfall in the language of
the Inupiat, Alaska's northernmost peoples.
It is so named because when viewed from
the north, the mountain resembles the balanced log
of a deadfall trap.
Soukikpak is a monolith of pure limestone thrust
into the sky.
Limestone forms in tropical marine environments, which means
that, yes, strange as it may seem, a
page of the Brooks Range story includes a
time when a warm shallow sea covered the
land. Fossils of clams, coral, and other marine
creatures can be found even on the high
ridges of the Brooks Range.
During this journey along the Dalton, you may
have noticed that sometimes the pipeline courses alongside
us, and sometimes it disappears entirely. Where does
it go?
That is part of the genius of the
pipeline's engineering.
420 miles of the pipeline is insulated and
elevated above ground. This was done in areas
where the oil's heat could melt the permafrost
and destabilize the pipeline. The rest of the
pipeline's 380 miles is buried underground.
We climbed steadily into the Brooks Range, and
the trees are still holding on for now,
but we are rapidly approaching another big milestone
in the journey, the moment we cross the
tree line.
The Arctic tree line is one of the
most significant ecological boundaries on our planet. It
circles the globe's northern landmasses, marking the point
at which conditions are simply too harsh for
trees to grow.
The tree line is not a hard, linear
boundary like the Arctic Circle. It is dynamic,
shifting with the conditions and contours of the
land. In fact, this stretch of the Dalton
is ground 0 for scientists currently studying the
tree line's rapid progression north as the climate
warms.
As we climb, we can feel it. The
tree line must be close and sure enough,
it's right around the bend.
We round the corner and the spruce trees
are gone. A few tall shrubs hang on,
and then quite suddenly,
we're crossing the tree line.
We just climbed onto the Chandelar Shelf, a
broad glacial valley that acts much like a
stepping stool into the range. We are now
officially past the tree line at 32 100
feet and climbing.
This valley is a major avalanche zone in
the winter. The pipeline lies buried to our
right, too precious to risk destruction from slides.
Throughout the winter, artillery shells are used to
clear the slopes above the highway. Just another
example of how the reality of this highway
changes with the seasons.
Even with these incredibly good driving conditions today,
we feel the risk of this road. On
the Dalton, the rules are very clear. Truckers
have the right of way. If we have
to share the road with anyone here, we'll
be the ones sliding in thick mud. And
we know how our bus handles in mud,
not well.
Luckily we make it through without meeting anyone,
but it does feel a bit out of
the frying pan and into the fire, because
we are rapidly approaching one of the biggest
tests of the Dalton.
Adagan Pass, Alaska's highest year round mountain pass,
a steep, unrelenting climb to the summit, fighting
12% grades and loose gravel, all on a
slender ribbon cut into the mountainside.
The margin for error here is 0.
We have been on edge about this moment
because up here, even high summer can't protect
you from dangerous road conditions.
Snow falls year round and rain can transform
the pass into a slick muddy slide with
little to no visibility.
We are hyper aware that we are asking
a lot of this old bus.
But you know what?
She rocks
it.
After a 2.5 mile climb, Adigun Pass tops
out at 47 100 feet in elevation, the
highest point on the Dalton Highway.
Now, the descent begins.
Another 2.5 miles of equally steep downhill grades
on an equally narrow ribbon of road.
Coming up was a test of Bobbie's engine.
Now comes the test of her brakes.
Breathing a big and grateful sigh of relief,
the road levels out beneath us and we
come out into Adogan Valley. Our bus made
it through and we are ready for the
next stage of the journey.
Crossing Adogan Pass and dropping down into the
northern side of the Brooks Range is, in
a very real way, like entering a whole
different world.
We have entered a treeless world of blinding
extremes where frozen ground and sunlight dictate every
rule life must follow to survive.
And in crossing Edin Pass, we traversed yet
another significant boundary on planet Earth.
The Great Divide of the Americas splits North
and South America in 2, stretching from Alaska
to Chile. On the eastern side of the
divide, all rivers lead to one ocean. On
the western side, they lead to another.
Before Adagan Pass, every river we saw eventually
ends in the Pacific or the Bering Sea.
Now, here on this side, every waterway we
see is destined for the Arctic Ocean.
To our right, the Adagin River braids along
the valley floor right at the beginning of
its journey to the Arctic Ocean.
The river seems as fitting a companion as
any for a couple nights stay in the
Brooks Range.
Got some flowers. Oh, those are beautiful.
I made you some tea. Oh, thank you.
My pleasure.
Cheers.
It's funny how perspective works.
Camped here within the very spine of the
range, we are surrounded by a burst of
life. Wildflowers are in full bloom, green carpets
the ground and creeps as high up the
mountains as it can go.
It's easy to forget that this version of
events is extremely fleeting.
Life up here has just a few short
months to awaken, reproduce, then prepare for the
deep freeze once more.
We are witnessing a land in the maddest
of scrambles before the sun disappears and the
long darkness returns.
The range begins to show its other face.
It's mid July, but that means nothing here.
A cold wet wind sweeps down from the
peaks, chilling and reminding us where we really
are.
Our goal today is to make it all
the way through the range and catch a
glimpse of what lies beyond. The broad glacially
carved corridor of Adigun Valley is our path
out of the mountains.
We witness the relentless movement of freight to
and from the oil fields, and marvel at
the grit of the Daltons' truckers.
We have the luxury of waiting to drive
on good days. They don't.
Through mud, blizzards, squalls, and sub zero temperatures,
they haul. Driving this road in the summer
has its challenges. We can't even imagine taking
it on in winter.
The mountains here tell a story written in
dramatic and tilted layers. About a 150000000 years
ago, the collision of 2 tectonic plates thrust
all that ancient seabed into the sky. Layers
that were once horizontal were folded, twisted, and
tilted, and in some cases, even inverted.
As strange as it may seem, here the
sedimentary layers of this ancient seabed are upside
down.
It's hard to drive for miles alongside the
pipeline and not marvel at the speed with
which it was completed. When oil was discovered
in Prudhoe Bay in 1968, the country was
in the midst of an energy crisis. So
the rally around this project was swift and
spared no expense. It took 5 months to
build the road and only 3 years to
complete the pipeline.
We made it through the Brooks Range, and
the next stage of the journey awaits, but
we're tired. So we decide to camp and
rest up for the night.
We awake near the shores of Galbraith Lake,
all that remains of a glacial lake that
once filled Adogan Valley.
After that ancient seabed was thrust into the
sky, glaciers, wind, and time set to work.
Over the past 3000000 years, the Brooks Range
has been glaciated 3 times, carving it into
the form we see today.
We are surrounded by an unfathomable amount of
wilderness in every direction.
Gates of the Arctic National Park lies to
the west, and the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge
to the east. Combined, they protect over 28,000,000
acres of the Brooks Range and North Slope,
a North Slope that now awaits right at
our doorstep.
We've been blessed with another incredible driving day,
and we're taking it.
We now enter the 3rd and final ecoregion
of the journey, the one which will prove
most unfamiliar of all. The sun is shining,
spirits are high, and then we make our
first big error on the Dalton.
We get cocky.
After our bus killed it on Atigun Pass,
we're thinking that it's all literally downhill from
here.
Then we hit roadwork with single lane traffic
and deep slippery mud.
Here is where we get our first real
true taste of what this road can become
when conditions aren't ideal,
and it's not fun.
This is the first time we feel a
little trepidation about the drive back. What if
we don't get the same conditions on the
way back down the Dalton?
With the sketchy roadwork behind us, we can
breathe out and take in the strange foreign
world that is the North Slope.
The North Slope is aptly named. A long
gentle slope of Arctic Tundra stretching as far
as the eye can see, leading from the
edge of the Brooks Range down to the
Arctic Ocean.
Only low ground hugging vegetation can survive the
fierce wind, dark, and cold of this region.
Here, snow falls year round, there are only
6 weeks of summer without frost, and the
sun never rises from November 18th to January
23rd.
We are not the only ones making our
way down to sea level. The Sag River
courses to our right, one of the major
waterways of the North Slope. Sag is short
for Sagavenirktok,
an Inupiat word for swift current.
Strange fishes swim these waters, species like Arctic
grayling and Arctic charr. In a way, we
are now reunited with Adegan River. It joined
the Sagar River 20 miles upstream.
About 60 miles from the ocean, the North
Slope levels out onto a wide coastal plain.
Imagine driving for days on rough, rustic road,
and then suddenly, it shifts to this.
The last stretch of the Dalton is pristine,
almost like an award for making it this
far unscathed.
To be here in this place is a
big moment for our journey across the Americas.
To venture this far North was always a
gamble, a risk we took on, and we're
so happy that we did.
The coastal plain of the North Slope is
a truly fascinating place where strange animals roam
and even stranger features mark the landscape.
Little do we know just how much of
this place is about to reveal itself to
us.
With only 5 inches of rain per year,
the coastal plains should be as dry as
the Atacama Desert, and yet, it is a
vast, marshy wetland stretching as far as the
eye can see. How can that be?
It's all because of the permafrost.
Permafrost is ground that stays frozen for 2
years or more. While about a foot of
soil, called the active layer, thaws and refreezes
every year, the underlying permafrost does not. Here,
the permafrost forms an impenetrable barrier beneath the
coastal plain, trapping water on the surface.
The wetland it creates is a boon for
migratory birds who flock here from across the
world. They come from Asia, Africa, South America,
even Antarctica.
In summer, the plain bursts into life, providing
a short lived but bountiful buffet of small
fish and insects, grasses, and sedges.
Here on the coastal plain, the permafrost can
reach up to 2,000 feet thick. Ice does
strange things to the land here, both below
and above the surface. Ice wedge polygons are
one of those bizarre features. They form when
the ground contracts and cracks in winter similar
to a dry lake bed. The following summer,
water fills the cracks just to refreeze and
further force the ground apart come winter. It
takes centuries, but eventually enough freeze thaw cycles
will turn an otherwise uniformed landscape into this.
Another ice formed feature rises in the distance,
a lonely hill in an otherwise flat landscape.
This is a pingo. Once upon a time,
this pingo was a shallow pond that insulated
and kept the ground beneath it from fully
freezing. When the pond dried up, the permafrost
encroached, encircling and then squeezing water from the
unfrozen soil. This squeezing forced the water upwards
where it froze in an icy mass that
pushed up the land above it.
Migratory birds are one thing, but it's hard
to imagine large mammals eking out living in
this marshy land, and yet they do.
It's not only birds that take advantage of
the Coastal Plains bounty.
Alaska is home to 31 Caribou herds that
migrate with the seasons, following food and the
best place to birth their young. In summer,
they feast on tundra plants, mushrooms, sedges, and
willow. In the fall, they will migrate to
the Brooks Range and survive mainly on lichen.
Calves are born in early June and must
grow quickly to prepare for the fast approaching
winter. Healthy females give birth to 1 calf
per year, spending their summers caring for their
current generation, then rut begins in the fall
and the cycle starts all over again.
By late August, bulls will begin to shed
the velvet on their antlers, marking the start
of the breeding season and the fall migration
South. Once in migration mode, caribou herds can
cover a surprising amount of ground, traveling up
to 50 miles per day.
Mosquitoes constantly harass caribou, to the extent that
scientists believe migration patterns take this bothersome nuisance
into account.
North Slope caribou come to the windswept coastal
plain seeking relief, and they often climb to
higher ground, even elevated road beds, to catch
a break from the bugs.
Out here on the coastal plain, the Sag
River spreads out wide, braiding unhindered across the
land.
One Arctic creature loves to congregate in the
patches of brush hugging the river.
Musk oxen are supremely adapted to the harsh
conditions of the Arctic. Their secret is a
dense underlayer called Kiveot. Kiveot is a prized
and valuable fiber, softer than cashmere and 8
times warmer than wool.
Their Kivyot is covered by long, coarse guard
hairs that protect against snow, wind, and ice.
Both males and females have horns, but those
of males spread out at the base forming
a thick 4 inch cap of horn with
3 inches of bone under that. This protects
the brain when bulls engage in fierce battles
during rut.
At the end of the last ice age,
musk oxen roamed widely across Northern Europe, Greenland,
Asia, and North America. But by the 19
twenties, only a handful of herds remained in
the world. In 1930, 34 animals were brought
from Greenland to Nunavuk Island, Alaska, where they
thrived. That population was used to successfully reestablish
herds across the state, and now more than
4,000 musk oxen exist in Alaska.
It's hard not to get lost in wonder
witnessing this landscape and the creatures that call
it home. We do start to see infrastructure
in the distance, which can only mean one
thing. We are about to arrive in Deadhorse,
heart of Alaska's energy sector and the end
of the Dalton Highway.
It's pretty remarkable that we can even come
here. The Hall Road was opened to the
public in 1981, the same year it was
named after James w Dalton, an Alaskan engineer
heavily involved in Arctic oil exploration. But at
that time, it was only open to Suikitpack
Mountain. It wasn't until 1994 that noncommercial traffic
was allowed all the way here to Deadhorse.
In 1968, oil was discovered in Prudhoe Bay,
and both the Arctic and Alaska's economy were
changed forever.
Along with a haul road and pipeline, an
industrial camp was needed to support operations.
A company called Dead Horse Haulers was contracted
to provide the gravel for a landing strip,
and the name stuck.
Dead Horse is not a town. This place
is all business. Workers fly in for 2
to 3 week shifts, then fly home for
the same amount of time off. When they're
here, they work all day, every day.
There's a post office, general store, gas station,
and a few hotels. Everything else here speaks
to the massive operation underway. Since 1977, the
oil fields of Prudhoe Bay have produced 18,500,000,000
barrels of crude oil.
Filling the tank here represents a full loop
in the energy system. In a twist of
irony, fuel is very expensive right at the
place it is pumped out of the ground.
That is because the oil is not refined
here. It must be sent down the pipeline,
shipped from Valdez to refinery, then trucked all
the way back up the Dalton to arrive
here in its consumable form.
Here in Deadhorse, wildlife mingles with industry, a
bizarre juxtaposition and a reminder of just exactly
where we are.
The Arctic Ocean lies just a few miles
north. We are at the edge of North
America, and that is a pretty big milestone
for this old bus and these two artists.
We made it.
We are so happy that we made it
here in one piece, Bobby. It's amazing.
Throughout this journey, you've seen us add to
sticker collections at key landmarks. It's a beautiful
thing, this traveler's tradition. In a way, it
represents the intermingling of lives, paths, and stories.
All of these travelers drove the exact same
road, but our experiences and our stories are
as varied as the stickers before you.
In our story, this marks the end of
one chapter and the start of another. After
5 years on the road, we reached the
northernmost point we can drive in the Americas.
Now, the mission is to reach the southernmost
point all the way in Ushuaia, Argentina.
Between here and there, a whole world of
stories awaits.
And the Arctic Ocean? It's just a few
miles north, and we have a mind to
jump in those icy waters to kick off
the long journey to Argentina.
Join us as we literally dive in and
begin the next season and chapter of this
journey, next time on Art We There
Yet.
Hey, guys. If you enjoyed this video, be
sure to give us a like. Subscribe to
our channel. Send us a comment below. And
for exclusive content and behind the scenes view
of the Art We There Yet journey Join
us on Patreon. See you over on Patreon.