Keith.
And I thought my jokes were bad. Give
me one reason why I shouldn't have my
boy here pull your head off. How about
a magic trick?
I'm gonna make this pencil
disappear.
It's
it's
gone.
You wanna know how I got these scars?
My father was
a drinker
and a fiend.
And one night, he goes off crazier than
usual.
Mommy gets the kitchen knife to defend herself.
He doesn't like that. Not one bit.
So
me watching, he takes the knife to her,
laughing while he
does it. He turns to me
and he says,
why so serious?
He comes at me with the knife.
Why so serious?
He sticks the blade in my mouth.
Let's put a smile on that face.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
We are
tonight's entertainment.
I only have one question.
Where is Harvey Dent?
You know where Harvey is? Do you know
who he is? It's simple. We, kill the
Batman.
If it's so simple, why haven't you done
it already? If you're good at something, never
do it for free.
How much you will?
Half.
You're crazy. I'm not.
No, I'm not.
Okay, stop.
Why, hello, beautiful.
You must be Harvey's squeeze.
And you are beautiful.
Well, you look nervous.
Is it the scars?
You wanna know how I got them?
Come here.
Hey. Look at me.
So I had a wife. You look beautiful
like you.
Who tells me
I worry too much?
Who tells me I ought to smile more?
Who gambles and gets in deep? The sharks.
I mean,
one day they carve her face.
We have no money for surgeries.
She can't take it.
I just wanna see her smile again.
I just want her to know that I
don't care about the scars.
So
I stick a razor in my mouth and
do this
to myself.
And you know what?
She can't stand the sight of me.
She leaves.
Now I see the funny side.
Now I'm always smiling.
A little fighting you. I like that. Evening,
commissioner.
Harvey Dent never made it home.
Of course not. What have you done with
him?
Me?
I was right here.
Who did you leave him with?
Your people?
Assuming, of course, that they are still your
people,
and not Marrone's.
Does it depress you, commissioner,
to know
just how alone you really are?
Does it make you feel responsible for Harvey
Dent's current predicament? Where is he?
What's the time? What difference does that make?
Well, depending on the time, he may be
in one spot or several.
Hi.
You know,
I don't want there to be any hard
feelings between us, Harvey. When you and,
Rachel Rachel. Rachel were being abducted,
I was sitting in Gordon's cage.
No. I didn't read those charges. You're a
man. You're a plan. Do I really look
like a guy with a plan?
You know what I am? I'm a dog
chasing cars. I wouldn't know what to do
with one if I caught it. You know,
I just do things.
The mob has plans. The cops have plans.
Gordon's got plans.
You know, they're schemers.
Schemers trying to control their little worlds.
I'm not a schemer. I try to show
the schemers how pathetic
their attempts to control things really are.
So
when I say, weird. When I say that
you and your girlfriend was nothing personal,
you know that I'm telling the truth.
Never start with the head. The victim gets
all fuzzy. You can't feel the neck.
See?
You wanted me. Here I am. You let
5 people die.
Then, you let Dent take your place.
Even to a guy like me, that's cold.
Where's Dent? Those mob fools want you gone
so they can get back to the way
things were.
But I know the truth. There's no going
back. You've changed things
forever. Then why do you wanna kill me?
I don't wanna kill you. What would I
do without you? Go back to ripping off
mob dealers? No. No. No. No. You.
You complete
me. You're garbage who kills for money. Don't
talk like one of them. You're not.
Even if you'd like to be.
To them, you're just a freak.
Like me.
They need you right now.
And when they don't,
they'll cash you out. Like a leper.
See their morals, their code.
It's a bad joke.
Dropped at the first sign of trouble.
They're only as good as the world allows
them to be. I'll show you. When the
chips are down,
these,
these civilized people, they'll eat each other.
See, I'm not a monster.
I'm just ahead of the curve. I took
your little plan. I turned it on itself.
Look what I did to this city with
a few drums of gas and a couple
of bullets.
You know what I noticed? Nobody panics when
things go according to plan.
Even if the plan is horrifying.
If tomorrow I tell the press that like
a gang banger will get shot, or a
truckload of soldiers will be blowing up.
Nobody panics,
because it's all part of the plan.
But when I say that one little old
mayor will die,
Well, then everyone loses their minds.
You didn't think I'd risk losing the battle
for Gotham's soul in a fist fight with
you.
You need an ace in the hole.
Mine's Harvey.
What did you do?
I took Gotham's white knight,
and I
brought him down to our level.
It wasn't hard. See, madness, as you know,
is
like gravity.
All it takes is a little push.