The ocean,
the last frontier on Earth,
so much is unexplored
and unexplained.
To change that,
an exceptional team of incredibly talented specialists
is setting out to push the frontiers
of what we know about our oceans.
Oh my God.
Zoleka Filander,
deep-sea scientist.
Being a deep-sea researcher means having front-row tickets
to the best movie that everybody wants to watch.
Melissa Márquez,
shark biologist.
"Straight ahead, 12 o'clock."
"We just saw what no one has seen before."
Eric Stackpole,
ocean tech innovator.
"Scan now."
"I love building tools that allow us to see things in ways we've never seen before."
And Aldo Kane.
"This is absurd."
Former Royal Marine Special Ops.
"It doesn't get any more cutting-edge exploration than this."
Their secret weapon:
the Ocean Explorer,
the most technologically advanced research vessel ever built.
There's never been a more urgent need
to understand our ocean
and the animals that call it home,
because their lives
and ours
depend on it.
"Okay, here we go. Two o'clock, two o'clock."
This time, the team tracks sperm whales
down into an alien world
"What is that?"
full of fantastical creatures.
The Ocean Explorer is heading for deep water,
just off the Azores,
a chain of tiny volcanic islands
in the middle of the Atlantic,
and a rich oasis
for an abundance of marine life.
Every summer, nearly 1,000 sperm whales gather here.
They're easily identified by their distinctive sideways spout.
These whales spend most of their lives
deep below the surface.
But using the full scope of the Ocean
Explorer's tech,
the team hopes to shine a light on
their lives down in these black depths.
"Stand by, nine o'clock."
Sperm whales were hunted here as recently as
1987,
and they live up to 70 years,
so some of them may still remember that.
They're understandably
nervous around boats,
so Aldo and Melissa approach cautiously.
"You got your eyes on them?"
"They're sneaky, I tell you."
"Oh my God, they're right underneath us!
Right underneath us!"
"Wow, look at that!"
It's a whole family pod.
"That's gorgeous."
"That is a first for me."
"Yeah."
Sperm whales are the largest toothed predators on
the planet.
To study these giants up close and personal,
Aldo and Melissa join them beneath the waves.
Getting under the water and just seeing this
giant animal,
you can feel it
looking at you,
trying to figure out what the heck you
are.
But they won't have long.
Sperm whales spend just 20% of their lives
at the surface.
"When they dive, it's phenomenal."
"One swoosh of their tail and they are
gone."
These whales are diving a mile deep for
up to an hour at a time.
The buoyancy of their huge lungs and their
thick blubber should make that almost impossible.
But not only do they manage it, they
make it look effortless.
But exactly how they dive so deep has
never been filmed.
If the team can get a camera
on a whale, it could further their understanding.
They recruit the help of Rui Prieto,
a world-leading whale biologist. He's been studying
them in the Azores for over 20 years.
"We want to see
what they are actually doing
while they are underwater."
Eric sets to work helping Rui build a
camera tag that can withstand the immense pressure
of a sperm whale dive.
"Okay, so this is the power system,
and then
we've just got the little camera. You know,
the whole thing looks pretty simple, but I
mean, the thing that keeps going through my
mind is, you know, we're gonna have maybe
one window
and one chance of putting this together the
right way."
"So do you think that's something we can
do?" "Fingers crossed, right? I guess we'll find
out."
If they can pull this off, they'll get
the first-ever footage of a deep sperm whale
dive in the Azores.
"Yeah.
Let's turn a whale into a cameraman!"
"You have a green light." "Copy, green light.
Detach. We're off."
"We need to start looking for blows."
"Yeah."
"Oh, looks like there could be something over
there."
"Four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten. I count eleven whales here.
All in a tight cluster."
"Okay, here we go. Two o'clock, two o'clock.
You should have a pretty good eye at
three hundred, four hundred meters."
"Breaching."
"No."
"We think breaching might be a form of
communication between a sperm whale family. However, sometimes
it might just be the teenagers fooling around
and, you know, blowing off some steam."
"Let's go there very slowly."
"Slow and steady wins the race."
"Is that speed okay?" "Need to gain a
little bit on them because they are almost
diving."
When you're piloting a boat this close to
whales, there's absolutely
no room for error.
You're dealing with a live animal, so the
whole thing has to be
110% perfect or it's an aborted mission.
"That's it."
"Well done. Well done. Tag on."
"Ocean Explorer, this is Eagle Ray, over." "Eagle
Ray, Ocean Explorer. Go ahead."
"Tag deployed, and we will mark location on
the GPS."
"Copy that. Nice work."
The tag is designed to release after eight
hours and send a signal to help the
team locate it,
somewhere in the middle of the Atlantic.
"It is an intense feeling to spend all
this time on something and then watch it
just go into the abyss on the back
of a whale."
"What's this direction in front
of
us?"
"Confirm you have visual on the tag."
"Affirmative. We're looking at something orange in the
water. It could be the tag."
"Roger that. We are making our way to
your location now, Olga."
"I see it."
"We have visual on the tag."
"A little bit more, Olga. Yeah. There you
go. Right there."
"You got it?" "Yep. I have it." "I'm
dying to know, how does the tag look?"
"The tag does look in good condition, and
the camera looks like it is still dry."
"Yes."
"Alright. Great job, guys."
"Should I cut this?" "Yes, please."
"Now, it could be some water inside, so
we need to be careful."
"Very slowly."
"Very carefully."
"I'm, like, excited and nervous at the same
time, you know? Like, did everything work properly?
Did the batteries last?" "Yes, yes."
"Got it? Take it off."
"It's dry." "Okay." "And then there's our SD
card." "You got it?" "I got it.
This is it."
"This is what we've been working all this
time for." "Let's plug this into the computer
and see." "Okay, yeah, okay."
"Anything?"
"Anything that comes off this thing is new."
"Oh my God."
"That's the blowhole,
and it's going down because it's getting darker."
As they dive, sperm whales undergo an incredible
transformation.
The pressure of the water compresses their lungs,
and with less volume inside,
they become less buoyant,
allowing them to dive faster with minimum effort.
"As she dives faster, the force of the
water pushes the camera sideways."
"At 450
feet,
it flips."
"It's pointing backwards?" "Yeah, it's pointing backwards."
"We can actually see
the flukes beating."
Eric and Rui are the first people ever
to see a sperm whale use its body
and tail flukes
to dive into the deep.
"I'm learning a lot about how they actually
flex their flukes. It's very slow. It's very
calm."
Then, at 900
feet, the whale's behavior changes.
"Look, the tail stopped moving." "Yeah, it's
called gliding. They use the momentum
that they have to glide and save energy."
"I see. I've never seen it.
It's just amazing."
Its tail may have stopped moving, but this
whale is still diving.
With gravity doing the work, it can save
energy and preserve precious oxygen.
"Listen."
"It's hunting. This is the hunting sound." "Yeah."
Sperm whales use sound to hunt in the
dark.
When their sonar clicks hit an object and
bounce back,
the whale can locate a target over a
mile away.
"It's getting lighter in the background. Who knows
that?" "Yeah, the water is becoming clearer."
No luck this time, so the whale begins
its journey back to the surface.
"I hear a different, a slightly higher-pitched
clicking." "It was a coda."
"It's communicating with its family, just like Morse
code for whales."
"Another one. Someone is answering."
Each family unit has a unique coda
that can be heard from up to two
miles away.
"Wow, two, two, two. Another one."
This is how a surfacing whale reconnects with
its family.
"So you hear the codas, and then the
other one comes." "Yeah." "Do we know
that they do this?"
"We know that they talk to each other using
codas, but I've never seen them come together."
"Oh, I can't believe we got this."
"They are completely interacting."
"Nothing like that has ever been filmed."
"It's just amazing."
"We are seeing something that has never been
seen before.
These huge whales going to a part of
the world that we know almost nothing about,
and we get a first-person view. I'm
right next to Rui, and he spent his
entire life
trying to understand these animals, and this is
something he's never seen before."
Once back at the surface, some sperm whales
spend their time socializing.
Reestablishing
family bonds.
Others
grab a quick power nap.
But their time together is brief.
After just 15 minutes, they'll dive again
in their never-ending pursuit of prey.
Sperm whales eat up to a ton of
squid a day.
And with nearly 1,000 sperm whales here,
that's a lot of squid.
So what kind of squid are hiding down
there in the depths that could satisfy such
voracious appetites?
To find out, the team need to get
down there themselves.
[Due to character limitations, the transcript continues in the next message.]