The ocean.
The last frontier on Earth.
So much is unexplored
and unexplained.
To change that,
a kick-ass team of insanely talented specialists
is setting out to push the frontiers
of what we know
about our oceans.
Oh my gosh.
Zolekha Philander,
deep sea scientist.
Being a deep sea researcher means having front
row tickets to the best movie that everybody
wants to watch.
Melissa Marquez.
Straight ahead, 12 o'clock.
Shark biologist.
We just saw what no 1 has seen
before.
Eric Stackpole.
Scan now. Ocean tech innovator. I love building
tools that allow us to see things in
ways we've never seen before.
And Aldo Kane,
former Royal Marine Special Ops.
It doesn't get any more cutting edge exploration
than this. Their secret weapon,
the Ocean Explorer.
The most technologically advanced research vessel ever
built.
There's never been a more urgent need to
understand our ocean
and the animals that call it home,
because their lives
and ours
depend on it.
OK, here we go. 2 o'clock, 2 o'clock.
This time, the team tracks sperm whales
down into an alien world...
What is that?
...Full of fantastical
creatures.
No!
The ocean explorer is heading for deep water,
just off the Azores,
a chain of tiny volcanic
in the middle of the Atlantic,
and a rich oasis
for an abundance of marine life. Music
music
music Every summer, nearly a thousand sperm whales
gather here.
They're easily identified by their distinctive sideways
spout.
These whales spend most of their lives deep
below the surface.
But using the full scope of the Ocean
Explorers' tech,
the team hopes to shine a light on
their lives
down in these black depths.
Stand by at 09:00. Stand by at 9
o'clock.
Sperm whales were hunted here as recently as
1987,
and they live up to 70 years, so
some of them may still remember that.
They're understandably
nervous around boats,
So Aldo and Melissa approach cautiously.
You got your eyes on them?
They're sneaky, I tell you.
Oh! 0, my god, they're right underneath us.
They're right underneath us.
Wow, look at that.
It's a whole family pod.
That's
gorgeous. That is a first for me.
Yeah. Sperm whales are the largest toothed predator
on the planet. Predator on the planet.
To study these giants up close and personal,
Aldo and Melissa join them beneath the waves.
Getting under the water and just seeing this
giant animal,
you can feel it
looking at you,
trying to figure out what the heck you
are.
But they won't have long.
Sperm whales spend just 20% of their lives
at the surface.
When they dive, it's phenomenal. When they dive,
it's phenomenal.
1 swoosh of their tail and they are
gone.
These whales are diving a mile deep for
up to an hour at a time.
The buoyancy of their huge lungs and the
thick blubber should make that almost impossible.
But not only do they manage it, they
make it look effortless.
Cuckoo
clock
ticking But exactly how they dive so deep
has never been filmed.
If the team can get a camera on
a whale, It could further their understanding.
They recruit the help of Rui Prieto,
a world-leading whale
biologist. He's been studying them in the Azores
for over 20 years.
We want to see
what they are actually doing
while they are underwater.
Eric sets to work helping Rui build a
camera tag that can withstand the immense pressure
of a sperm whale dive.
OK, so this is the power system.
And then
we've just got the little camera. You know,
the whole thing looks pretty simple. But I
mean, the thing that keeps going through my
mind is, you know, we're going to have
maybe 1 window
and 1 chance of putting this together the
right way. So do you think that's something
we can do? Fingers crossed, right? I guess
we'll find out.
If they can pull this off, they'll get
the first-ever
footage of a deep sperm whale dive in
the Azores. Yeah.
Let's turn a whale into a cameraman.
You have a green light.
Copy, green light. Good deck, We're off.
We need to start looking for blows.
Yeah. OK. Yeah.
Looks like there could be something over there.
4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.
I count 11 whales here, all in a
tight cluster. OK, here we go. 2 o'clock,
2 o'clock.
You should have a pretty good eye, 300,
400 meters.
Breaching.
No!
We think breaching might be a form of
communication between a sperm whale family. However, sometimes
it might just be the teenagers fooling around
and, you know, blowing off some steam.
Let's go there very slowly.
Slow and steady wins the race.
Is that speed OK? Need to gain a
little bit on them, because they are almost
diving.
When you're piloting a boat this close to
Wales,
there's absolutely
no room for error.
You're dealing with a live animal, so the
whole thing has to be 110%
perfect, or it's an aborted mission.
That's it.
Well done.
Well done, dude. Tag on.
Ocean Explorer, this is Eagle Ray, over. Eagle
Ray, Ocean Explorer, go ahead.
Tag deployed and we will mark location on
the GPS.
Copy that. Nice work.
The tag is designed to release after 8
hours and send a signal to help the
team locate it,
somewhere in the middle of the Atlantic.
It is an intense feeling to spend all
this time on something and then watch it
just go into the abyss on the back
of a whale.
Oh, what's this direction in front of us?
Confirm you
have
visual on the tag. Affirmative.
We're looking at something orange
in the water. It could
be the tag.
Roger that. We are making our way to
your location now. Over.
Oh, I see it.
We have visual on the tag.
Little bit more, Aldo. Yeah, there you go.
Right there.
You got it? Yeah, got it.
I'm dying to know, how does a tag
look?
The tag does look in good condition, and
the camera looks like it's still dry. Yes.
All right, great job, guys.
Should I cut this? Yes, please.
Now it could be some water inside, so
we need to be careful.
Very slowly,
very carefully.
I'm like excited and nervous at the same
time, you know, like, did everything work properly?
Did the batteries last? Yes, yes.
Got it? Take it off.
It's dry.
OK. And then there's our SD card.
You got it? I got it. This is
it.
This is what we've been working all this
time for. Let's plug this to the computer
and see. Okay, yeah. Okay.
Anything that comes off this thing is new.
Oh my god!
That's the blowhole.
And it's going down because it's getting darker.
As they dive, sperm whales undergo an incredible
transformation.
The pressure of the water compresses their lungs.
And with less volume inside,
they become less buoyant,
allowing them to dive faster with minimum effort.
As she dives faster, the force of the
water pushes the camera sideways.
At 450
feet,
it flips.
It's pointing backwards? Yeah, it's pointing backwards.
We can actually see
the flukes beating.
Eric and Rui are the first people ever
to see a sperm whale use its body
and tail flukes to dive into the deep.
I'm learning a lot about how they actually
flex
their flukes.
It's very slow. It's very calm.
Then, at 900 feet, the whale's behavior changes.
Look. The tail stopped moving. Yeah. It's called
gliding. They use the
momentum that they have to glide and keep
energy. I see. And I've never seen it.
So
it's just amazing.
Its tail may have stopped moving, but this
whale is still diving.
With gravity doing the work, it can save
energy and preserve precious oxygen.
Listen.
It's
hunting. This is the hunting sound. Yeah.
Sperm whales use sound to hunt in the
dark.
When their sonar clicks hit an object and
bounce back,
the whale can locate a target over a
mile away.
It's getting lighter in the background. You notice
that? Yeah, the water is becoming clear.
No luck this time,
so the whale begins its journey back to
the surface.
I hear a different, slightly higher-pitched clicking. It
was a coda.
It's communicating with its family, just like Moore's
code for whales.
Another 1. Someone is answering.
Each family unit has a unique coda
that can be heard from up to 2
miles away.
Whoa, 2222,
another 1.
This is how a surfacing whale reconnects with
its family.
So you hear the codas, and then the
other 1 comes in. Yeah, yeah. Do we
know that they do this? We know that
they talk to each other using codas, but
I've never seen them come together.
They are completely interacting. They are completely interacting.
Nothing like that has ever been filmed.
It's just amazing.
We are seeing something that has never been
seen before.
These huge whales going to a part of
the world that we know almost nothing about,
and we get a first-person view. I'm right
next to Rui, and he's spent his entire
life trying to understand these animals, and this
is something he's never seen before.
Once back at the surface, some sperm whales
spend their time socializing,
reestablishing Reestablishing
family bonds.
Others
grab a quick power nap.
But their time together is brief.
After just 15 minutes, they'll dive again
in their never-ending pursuit of prey.
Sperm whales eat up to a ton of
squid a day.
And with nearly a thousand sperm whales here,
that's a lot of squid.
So what kind of squid are hiding down
there in the depths that could satisfy such
voracious appetites?
To find out, the team need to get
down there themselves.
MUSIC
The mission will be led by Zolekka,
the ocean explorer's deep sea researcher.
For this mission, I'm partnering with Edie Witter,
1 of the world's most experienced deep sea
biologists.
You ready to dive?
Yes.
So Neptune, we are ready to shut edges
So bridge you are clear to roll some
out
Edie's been pushing the envelope in ocean exploration
for over 40 years.
That's left-hand in the water.
Venting now.
Depth to 0 meters, vent secure, descending, over.
Every time we dive into the deep, we
are heading into the unknown.
We are explorers
and this is our spaceship.
600 feet down the team enters the Twilight
Zone,
a world dominated by darkness a world dominated
by darkness
and alien creatures. Oh, look at that.
Look at that.
What are you seeing?
It's
a
glass
squid,
a rare sighting. Exciting.
Being transparent,
that's defense mechanism.
It's such an amazing adaptation.
You see it a lot in the ocean,
but you don't see it much on land.
At 1, 500 feet, they find even more
signs of life.
What is that?
What?
Look. Turn to the right. Turn to the
right.
It's ink, But it's so much. Oh, my
god.
Where is the squid, though?
Oh, squid. Squid.
A bird squid.
Hello.
Hello. And this 1 has attitude. Oh, my
gosh. It's winter. Beautiful.
Oh, look at him. He's not going anywhere.
Winter.
I think he's trying to eat Zalecka.
Yeah.
It's
good
food.
It's
squid
food.
As the sub dives to 2, 500 feet,
Zaleckha
spots something extraordinary.
Oh, my word.
Is that a whiplash squid?
Look how exquisite it is.
All squid can change color by expanding or
contracting cells in their skin, called chromatophores.
Do you think
it's signaling
to other squid?
Is this an alarm signal?
How does 1 even decode
what we're really seeing here?
I'd like to think I'm a level-headed scientist,
but wow,
when you come across
an encounter like this,
it's absolutely stunning.
Absolutely
stunning.
This is why we do it, Edie.
Sperm whales do prey on whiplash squid, but
they're so small, they'd need to eat thousands
every day.
At 3, 300 feet, they approach the boundary
of the Midnight Zone.
The Midnight Zone is pitch black, and it's
freezing.
But as hostile as this place is, this
is where the sperm whale finds its food.
So it's important that we go take a
look down there.
But the sub reaches its maximum dive depth.
It can't go any farther.
Control, control.
Neptune passing 5, 0 meters clear to surface.
If they want to search the Midnight Zone
for larger sperm whale prey,
The team will have to mobilize the ship's
ROV,
a remotely operated vehicle.
The ROV is capable of going to depths
of 20, 000 feet, So getting to 5,
000 feet where the sperm whales are going
should be no problem at all.
Melissa baits the ROV with deep water squid's
favorite meal,
Other squid.
And that is a squid ready to be
lifelike
in the water column. The
the
Through its tether to the ship, the ROV
sends back a live picture.
Exploring the deep, you often see something that
you have never seen before, but you hope
that you're going to see something no 1
has seen before.
Lights off.
Oh, incoming, incoming. What's off? Oh, incoming, incoming.
Here we go. Whoa.
What is
that? Bingo. Kitefin shark.
The
squid lure has drawn in
more than the team bargained for.
He looks like a good size.
These guys can get up to, like, 30
pounds on average.
Sperm whales, yeah, they do eat them, but
actually have a preference for squid.
After hours in the deep and just 1
encounter with the kite fin,
the team wonders if the noise from the
ROV could be scaring off the squid.
Time to try a different approach.
Marine
biologist Nathan Robinson
has the perfect camera rig for this mission.
The Angler is a stealth camera, makes
no noise. It's also very
light sensitive. So this actually really is perfect
for seeing animals in the deep sea. In
the deep sea.
Going down.
Hey, keep letting it go.
Luring
The angler on a fishing line may look
low tech, but this is our secret weapon.
It can dive to 6, 500
feet
and then just sit there
completely silent and still
so as not to scare away any wildlife.
The angler is armed with an E-jelly,
an LED array that mimics the defense mechanism
of the Atolla jellyfish, which
lights up when threatened to try and attract
an even larger predator in the hope
that it will scare off the attacker.
After hours in the deep, the rig is
ready to be retrieved.
Only once back aboard will the team discover
if their covert mission has been a success.
All right, You ready to bring it to
the lab? Yeah.
OK, so now we're going down to the
bottom.
Oh, my God. What a catch.
These flying squid are known sperm whale prey.
We've been seeing a ton
of squid conducting these hit
and run attacks on the bait and the
E. Jellie.
They are large,
very nutritious
food items for something like a sperm whale.
Hours into the footage, Nathan and Eric spot
something even larger,
and they gather the rest of the team.
Just watch this.
That is a really big squid.
So this species is the third largest in
the oceans.
Dana octopus squid is the common name. It's
got light organs on the ends of its
arms
that are like the size of lemons.
Look at them. They're glowing so bright.
Why would you have such bright lights there?
To blind you. Like a deer in the
headlights.
So you've got your little critter, your little
crustacean that you want to eat.
You shine these big kind of lemon-sized lights
right out.
It can't see what's coming from what direction,
and then bam, you take it down.
Weighing as much as a full-grown gorilla,
a sperm whale only needs to hunt 5
of these giants a day.
This is actually
the
most common
species that sperm whales eat in terms of
weight. This is actually
staple food. This is number 1 thing in
their diet. But they've hardly ever been seen.
I'm actually pretty sure this is the first
footage we have of day-not-to-be-squid
in the Atlantic.
This is amazing.
Thanks to the deep water team, we've seen
squid down there
large enough
to feed this huge population of sperm whales.
But what's fueling this rich ecosystem?
It's all down to the tiniest organisms in
the ocean.
When deep ocean currents hit the island's underwater
slopes,
nutrient-rich water is forced up toward the surface.
These nutrients feed microorganisms
that form the base of the food web.
And the more there are, the more life
this ecosystem can support.
To find out just how rich these waters
are,
Edie and Zolekka once again take a dive
into the deep.
The density of this microscopic
life is difficult to judge in these dark
waters.
But Edie has a magic trick to reveal
it. MUSIC PLAYS
600 metres.
Oh, I hope this works.
OK, you ready?
321,
lights coming on.
Nothing.
Let's drop down.
Control Neptune,
we are ascending. Okay, let's try
it again.
Okay,
let's try it again.
Okay, 321, lights coming
on.
Oh!
Whoo!
It worked!
Ha-ha-ha-ha!
Wow!
Bioluminescence in action. Fire, luminescence in action.
It's like I'm wrapped in a blanket of
stars.
This is the base of the full chain.
The fish eat the plankton
and the squid eat the fish.
And then the sperm whales are fitting on
the squid,
this is where it all begins.
Smallest
to the biggest.
That's
fantastic. Edie's witnessed this bioluminescent
phenomenon her entire career,
but has never had the technology to share
it with the world...
Until now.
Wow, thanks, Edie. You got it.
It's like having seen UFOs,
and now suddenly there's evidence.
OK, can we do that again?
Absolutely.
Without this abundance of tiny life,
the squid and the sperm whales couldn't survive
here. It's very, very humbling to think that
no matter how tiny you are, you can
do gigantic
things.
Control control net tunes ascending. Over. Gigantic things.
Control, control, Neptune's ascending, over.
Clear the surface, clear the surface. Welcome back,
Neptune.
Blow your tanks.
Where did you enjoy that dive? Oh, are
you kidding?
That was actually on my bucket list.
You know, as I get older, every expedition
I go on, I figure this might be
the last.
And
if this is the last, it's the best.
It's just been absolutely amazing. Absolutely amazing.
In their time here in the
Azores, the team has captured the first ever
images of a sperm whale diving into these
deep waters.
This is the culmination of a huge amount
of effort and many sleepless nights. But At
the end of the day, we got those
few minutes of incredibly
priceless footage
that made the whole thing worth it.
It was awesome.
They've added to the image catalog of the
squid that feed the sperm whales.
Thanks to the Ocean Explorer, we've been able
to dive deep into the world of sperm
whales here and discovered this interaction between them
and massive squid that's never really been observed
here before, which is pretty mind-blowing.
And they've documented the normally invisible riches
that fuel this entire ecosystem.
It's
fabulous. I am 1 of the few
people to witness a bi-luminescence
light show. And I'm so excited to share
this with the world.
That is mind blowing.
We've still got so much to learn about
these whales, but seeing them live in harmony,
they could definitely teach us a thing or
2. No!
From the largest...
...To the tiniest creatures.
The team has made significant discoveries here in
the Azores.
Nothing like that has ever been filmed.
A rich hot spot for life in the
Atlantic,
and a blueprint for healthy oceans
everywhere.