The ocean,
the last frontier on earth,
so much is unexplored
and unexplained.
To change that,
a kickass team of insanely talented specialists
is setting out to push the frontiers
of what we know about our oceans.
Oh my god.
Zoelleke Philander,
deep sea scientist.
Being a deep sea researcher means having front
row tickets
to the best movie that everybody wants to
watch.
Melissa Marquez Straight ahead, 12 o'clock. Shark biologist
We just saw what no one has seen
before.
Eric Stackpole
Scan now. Ocean tech innovator I love building
tools that allow us to see things in
ways we've never seen before.
And Aldo Kane
This is absurd.
Former Royal Marine Special Ops.
It doesn't get any more cutting edge exploration
than this. Their secret weapon,
the Ocean Explorer,
the most technologically advanced research vessel ever built.
There's never been a more urgent need to
understand our ocean
and the animals that call it home,
because their lives
and ours
depend on it.
Okay. Here we go. 2 o'clock. 2 o'clock.
This time, the team tracks sperm whales
down into an alien world
What is that?
Full of fantastical creatures.
The ocean explorer is heading for deep water,
just off the Azores.
A chain of tiny volcanic islands
in the middle of the Atlantic,
and a rich oasis
for an abundance of marine life.
Every summer, nearly a 1000 sperm whales gather
here.
They're easily identified by their distinctive sideways spout.
These whales spend most of their lives deep
below the surface.
But using the full scope of the Ocean
Explorer's tech,
the team hopes to shine a light on
their lives down in these black depths.
Stand by, 9 o'clock.
Sperm whales were hunted here as recently as
1987,
and they live up to 70 years, so
some of them may still remember that.
They're understandably
nervous around boats,
so Aldo and Melissa approach cautiously.
You got your eyes on them?
They're sneaky, I tell you.
Oh my god. They're right underneath us. They're
right underneath us.
Wow. Look at that.
It's a whole family pod.
That's gorgeous.
That is a first for me.
Yeah.
Sperm whales are the largest toothed predator on
the planet.
To study these giants up close and personal,
Aldo and Melissa join them beneath the waves.
Getting under the water and just seeing this
giant animal,
you can feel it
looking at you,
trying to figure out what the heck you
are.
But they won't have long.
Sperm whales spend just 20% of their lives
at the surface.
When they dive, it's phenomenal.
One swoosh of their tail and they are
gone.
These whales are diving a mile deep for
up to an hour at a time.
The buoyancy of their huge lungs and the
thick blubber should make that almost impossible.
But not only do they manage it, they
make it look effortless.
But exactly how they dive so deep has
never been filmed.
If the team can get a camera
on a whale, it could further their understanding.
They recruit the help of Rui Prieto,
a world leading whale biologist. He's been studying
them in the Azores for over 20 years.
We want to see
what they are actually doing,
while they are underwater.
Eric sets to work helping Rui build a
camera tag that can withstand the immense pressure
of a sperm whale dive.
Okay. So this is the power system,
and then
we've just got the little camera. You know,
the whole thing looks pretty simple, but I
mean, the thing that keeps going through my
mind is, you know, we're gonna have maybe
one window
and one chance of putting this together the
right way.
So do you think that's, something we can
do? Fingers crossed. Right? I guess we'll find
out.
If they can pull this off, they'll get
the first ever footage of a deep sperm
whale dive in the Azores.
Yeah.
Let's turn a whale into a cameraman.
You have a green light. Copy green light.
Detect. We're off.
We need to start looking for blows.
Yeah.
Oh, looks like there could be something over
there.
4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10. I count 11 whales here.
All in a tight cluster.
Okay. Here we go. 2 o'clock. 2 o'clock.
You should have a pretty good eye at
3 100, 400 meters.
Breaching.
No.
We think breaching might be a form of
communication between a sperm whale family. However, sometimes
it might just be the teenagers fooling around
and, you know, blowing off some steam.
Let's go there very slowly.
Slow and steady wins the race.
Is that speed okay? Need to gain a
little bit on them because they are almost
diving.
When you're piloting a boat this close to
Wales, there's absolutely
no room for error.
You're dealing with a live animal, so the
whole thing has to be
110% perfect or it's an aborted mission.
That's it.
Well done. Well done, dude. Tag on.
Ocean Explorer, this is Eagle Ray over. Eagle
Ray, Ocean Explorer. Go ahead.
Tag deployed and we will mark location on
the GPS.
Copy that. Nice work.
The tag is designed to release after 8
hours and send a signal to help the
team locate it,
somewhere in the middle of the Atlantic.
It is an intense feeling to spend all
this time on something and then watch it
just go into the abyss on the back
of a whale.
What's this direction in front
of
us?
Confirm you have visual on the tag.
Affirmative. We're looking at something orange in the
water. It could be the tag.
Roger that. We are making our way to
your location now, Olga.
I see it.
We have visual on the tag.
A little bit more, Elga. Yeah. There you
go. Right there.
You got it? Yep. I have it. I'm
dying to know, how does the tag look?
The tag does look in good condition, and
the camera looks like it is still dry.
Yes.
Alright. Great job, guys.
Should I cut this? Yes, please.
Now it could be some water inside, so
we need to be careful.
Very slowly.
Very carefully.
I'm, like, excited and nervous at the same
time. You know? Like, did everything work properly?
Did the batteries last? Yes. Yes.
Got it? Take it off.
It's dry. Okay. And then there's our SD
card. You got it? I'm I got it.
This is it.
This is what we've been working all this
time for. Let's plug this to the computer
and see. Okay. Yeah. Okay.
Anything
that comes off this thing is new.
Oh, my god.
That's the the blowhole,
and it's going down because it's it's getting
darker.
As they dive, sperm whales undergo an incredible
transformation.
The pressure of the water compresses their lungs,
and with less volume inside,
they become less buoyant,
allowing them to dive faster with minimum effort.
As she dives faster, the force of the
water pushes the camera sideways.
At 450
feet,
it flips.
It's pointing backwards? Yeah. It's pointing backwards.
We can actually see
the flukes beating.
Eric and Rui are the first people ever
to see a sperm whale use its body
and tail flukes
to dive into the deep.
I'm learning a lot about how they actually
flex the their their flukes. It's very slow.
It's very
calm.
Then at 900 feet, the whales' behavior changes.
Look. The tail stopped moving. Yeah. It's it's
called gliding. They use the the the momentum
that they have to glide and keep energy.
I see. And I I've never seen it.
So it it it's just amazing.
Its tail may have stopped moving, but this
whale is still diving.
With gravity doing the work, it can save
energy and preserve precious oxygen.
Listen.
It's hunting. This is the hunting sound. Yeah.
Sperm whales use sound to hunt in the
dark.
When their sonar clicks hit an object and
bounce back,
the whale can locate a target over a
mile away.
It's getting lighter in the background. Who knows
that? Yeah. The the water is becoming clearer.
No luck this time, so the whale begins
its journey back to the surface.
I hear a different a slightly higher pitched
clicking. It was a coda.
It's communicating with its family just like Morse
code for whales.
Another one. Someone is answering.
Each family unit has a unique coda
that can be heard from up to 2
miles away.
Well, 2, 2, 2. Another one.
This is how a surfacing whale reconnects with
its family.
So you hear the codas, and then the
other one comes. Yeah. Yeah. Do we know
that they do this?
Know that they talk to each other using
codas, but I've never seen them come together.
Oh, I can't believe we got this off.
They are completely interacting.
Nothing like that has ever been filmed.
It's just amazing.
We are seeing something that has never been
seen before.
These huge whales going to a part of
the world that we know almost nothing about,
and we get a first person view. I'm
right next to Rui, and he spent his
entire life
trying to understand these animals, and this is
something he's never seen before.
Once back at the surface, some sperm whales
spend their time socializing.
Reestablishing
family bonds.
Others
grab a quick power nap.
But their time together is brief.
After just 15 minutes, they'll dive again
in their never ending pursuit of prey.
Sperm whales eat up to a ton of
squid a day.
And with nearly a 1000 sperm whales here,
that's a lot of squid.
So what kind of squid are hiding down
there in the depths that could satisfy such
voracious appetites
to find out the team need to get
down there themselves.
The mission will be led by Zulekha,
the ocean explorer's deep sea researcher.
For this mission, I'm partnering with Edi Wouda,
one of the world's most experienced deep sea
biologists.
You ready to dive?
Yes.
So Neptune, we are ready to
to show touches. SO bridge, you are clear
to roll sub out.
Eighty's been pushing the envelope in ocean exploration
for over 40 years.
That's Neptune in the border.
Venting now.
Depth, 2 0 meters. Vent secured. Descending. Over.
Every time we dive into the deep, we
are heading into the unknown.
We are explorers,
and this is our spaceship.
600 feet down, the team enters the twilight
zone.
A world dominated by darkness
and alien creatures.
Oh, look at that. Look at that.
What are you seeing?
It's a glass squid,
a rare sighting.
Being transparent,
that's a defense mechanism.
Such an amazing adaptation.
You see it a lot in the ocean,
but you don't see it much on land.
At 1500 feet, they find even more signs
of life.
What is that? 21. 1. Look. Just turn
to the right. Turn to the right. It's
ink, but it's so much. Oh my god.
Oh, yeah. That's a massive pool of ink.
Where's the squid though?
Oh, squid. Squid.
A bird squid.
Hello. I know. And this one has attitude.
Oh, my gosh. It's squid. Beautiful. Oh, look
at these.
I
think he's trying to eat saleka. Yeah.
It's good food.
As the sub dives to 25 100 feet,
Salehka spots something extraordinary.
Oh, my word.
Is that a whiplash squid?
Look how exquisite
it is. All squid can change color by
expanding or contracting cells in their skin
called chromatophores.
Do you think do you think it's signaling
to other squid?
No.
Is this an alarm signal?
How does one even decode
what we're really seeing here?
I'd like to think I'm a level headed
scientist,
but wow.
When you come across
an encounter like this,
it's absolutely stunning.
Absolutely stunning.
This is why we do it, Eddy.
Sperm whales do prey on whiplash squid, but
they're so small, they'd need to eat 1,000
every day.
At 33 100 feet, they approach the boundary
of the midnight zone.
The midnight zone is pitch black, and it's
freezing.
But as hostile as this place is, this
is where the sperm whale finds its food.
So it's important that we go take a
look down there.
But the sub reaches its maximum dive
depth. It can't go any farther.
Control. Control.
Neptune passing 50 meters, clear to surface.
If they want to search the midnight zone
for larger sperm whale prey,
the team will have to mobilize the ship's
ROV,
a remotely operated vehicle.
The ROV is capable of going to depths
of 20,000 feet. So getting to 5,000 feet
where the sperm whales are going should be
no problem at all.
Melissa baits the ROV with deepwater squid's favorite
meal,
other squid.
And that is a squid ready to be
lifelike
in the water
column.
Through its tether to the ship, the ROV
sends back a live picture.
Exploring the deep, you often see something that
you have never seen before, but you hope
that you're gonna see something no one has
seen before.
Lights off.
Oh, incoming incoming.
Here we go.
Woah. What what is that?
Bingo.
Kitefin shark.
The squid lure has drawn in more than
the team bargained for.
He looks like a good size.
These guys can get up to, like, £30
on average.
Sperm whales, yeah, they do eat them, but
actually have a preference for squid.
After hours in the deep and just one
encounter with the kite fin,
the team wonders if the noise from the
ROV could be scaring off the squid.
Time to try a different approach.
Marine biologist Nathan Robinson
has the perfect camera rig for this mission.
The angler is a stealth camera, makes
no noise. It's also very
light sensitive, so this actually really is perfect
for seeing animals in
the deep sea.
Going down.
Hey, keep letting
it
go. Lowering the angler on a fishing line
may look low tech, but this is our
secret weapon.
It can dive to 6 1,500
feet
and then just sit there
completely silent and still
so as not to scare away any wildlife.
The angler is armed with an e jelly,
an LED array that mimics the defense mechanism
of the Atolla jellyfish,
which lights up when threatened to try and
attract an even larger predator in the hope
that it will scare off the attacker.
After hours in the deep, the rig is
ready to be retrieved.
Only once back aboard will the team discover
if their covert mission has been a success.
Alright. You ready to bring it to the
lab? Yeah.
Okay. So now we're going down to the
bottom.
Oh, my god. What a catch.
These flying squid are known sperm whale prey.
We've been seeing a ton of squid conducting
these hit and run attacks on the baits
and the e jelly.
They are large,
very nutritious
food items for something like a sperm whale.
Hours into the footage, Nathan and Eric spot
something even larger,
and they gather the rest of the team.
Just watch this.
What? That is a really big squid. So
this species is the 3rd largest in the
oceans.
Dana octopus squid is the the common name.
It's got light organs on the ends of
its arms that are like the size of
lemons. Look at them. They're glowing so bright.
Why would you have such bright lights there?
To blind you. Oh, it's like a deer
in the headlights. Yeah. So you've got your
little critter, your little crustacean that you wanna
eat. You shine these big, kinda lemon sized
lights right at it. It can't see what's
coming from what direction, and then, bam, you
take it down.
Weighing as much as a full grown gorilla,
a sperm whale only needs to hunt 5
of these giants a day.
This is actually
the
most common,
species that sperm whales eat in terms of
weight. This is actually
simple food. This is number 1, in their
diet. They're eating. Yeah. But they've hardly ever
been seen. I'm actually pretty sure this is
the first footage we have of Dane octopus
squid in the Atlantic. This is amazing.
Thanks to the Deepwater team, we've seen squid
down there large enough
to feed this huge population of sperm whales.
But what's fueling this rich ecosystem?
It's all down to the tiniest organisms in
the ocean.
When deep ocean currents hit the island's underwater
slopes,
nutrient rich water is forced up toward the
surface.
These nutrients feed microorganisms
form the base of the food web.
And the more there are, the more life
this ecosystem can support.
To find out just how rich these waters
are,
Idi and Zuleka once again take a dive
into the deep.
The density of this microscopic life is difficult
to judge in these dark waters,
but Eddy has a magic trick to reveal
it.
600 meters.
Oh, I hope this works.
Okay. You ready?
Okay.
3, 2, 1. Lights coming on.
Nothing.
Let's drop down.
Control that tune, we are descending.
Okay.
Let's try it again.
Okay. 321. Lights coming
on.
Woo.
It worked.
Wow.
Bio luminescence
in action.
It's like I'm wrapped in a blanket of
stars.
This is the base of the food chain.
The fish eat the plankton,
and the squid eat the fish. And then
the sperm whales are feeding on the squid.
This is where it all begins,
smallest
to the biggest.
That's fantastic.
Edie's witnessed this bioluminescent
phenomenon her entire career,
It's like having seen UFOs, and now suddenly
there's evidence.
Okay. Can we do that again?
Absolutely.
Without this abundance of tiny life,
the squid and the sperm whales couldn't survive
here. It's very, very humbling to think that
no matter how tiny you are, you can't
do
gigantic things.
Control, control, Neptune's ascending over.
Clear the surface. Clear the surface. Welcome back,
Neptune.
Blow your tanks.
Oh, did you enjoy that day? Oh, are
you kidding? That was actually on my bucket
list.
You know, as I get older, every expedition
I go on, I figure this might be
the last.
And if this is the last, it's the
best.
It's just been absolutely amazing.
In their time here in the Azores,
the team has captured the first ever images
of a sperm whale diving into these deep
waters.
This is the culmination of a huge amount
of effort and many sleepless nights, but at
the end of the day, we got those
few minutes of incredibly priceless footage
that made the whole thing worth it.
It was awesome.
They've added to the image catalog of the
squid that feed the sperm whales.
Thanks to the Ocean Explorer, we've been able
to dive deep into the world of sperm
whales here and discovered this interaction between them
and massive squid that's never really been observed
here before, which is pretty mind blowing.
And they've documented the normally invisible riches
that fuel this entire ecosystem.
It's fabulous.
I am one of the few people to
witness a bioluminescence
light
show, and I'm so excited to share this
with the world.
That is mind blowing.
We've still got so much to learn about
these whales, but seeing them live in harmony,
they could definitely teach us a thing or
2.
No.
From the largest
to the tiniest creatures,
the team has made significant discoveries here in
the Azores.
Nothing like that has ever been filmed.
A rich hotspot for life in the Atlantic,
and a blueprint for healthy oceans
everywhere.